Hey guys, quick note before we get into the
video. I've been pretty busy moving between
states and working on my startup, Silo. So, my
brother is filling in for me on this video. Let
me know what you think in the comments. With
that out of the way, let's get right into it.
The rental car business just had its
best quarter in years… except for Hertz.
And the reason is pretty wild.
Their CEO said "Electric
vehicles are now mainstream."
Then soon after, dumped tens of
thousands of EVs, at a low price.
But, things have gotten so much worse, and
it seems like it’s entirely their fault.
EVs are now the saving grace
for the rental industry…
Hertz are also being sued
for misleading shareholders.
And now, their AI will bill customers for
fake damage… without any human review.
Everything keeps getting
worse and worse for Hertz.
So, how did it all happen?
How did things go from bad to worse?
Okay, let’s start with those EVs.
After that… bold announcement from
CEO Mark Fields, Hertz announced it was going
to add 100,000 Teslas to their fleet. And that
was just by the end of 2022. Of course,
the real number they got was about 35,000.
They also planned to buy 65,000 Polestar EVs
over five years, and were even planning to
add models from GM's electric brands later on.
A bold move, but Hertz needed one. They had just
emerged from bankruptcy the previous year.
They also did this for a few reasons.
First, they thought this would lower costs.
Gasoline prices were high and volatile.
Not only that, EVs promised significantly
lower overall maintenance costs.
No oil changes, no complex transmissions, and
fewer parts to break down meant less time in the
shop and more time on the road making money.
At least, that's how it seemed…
But there’s more.
The industry, at least at the time,
was giving clear signals that EVs were the future.
Tesla had just passed a $1 trillion market cap.
Their profits were skyrocketing.
The legacy automakers were now
pouring billions into battery factories.
So, it seemed that EVs were now mainstream,
to quote CEO Mark Fields.
But, things seemed to backfire,
in almost every way.
EVs don't need oil changes,
but they have other problems.
Hertz found that its repair
costs were actually 20% higher than for
comparable internal combustion vehicles.
If a Tesla gets in a minor collision, it often
requires specialized, expensive parts and
labor that only the manufacturer can provide.
Data showed that the maintenance and repair
costs for EVs were significantly higher
than for the gasoline cars in its fleet.
Plus while repair costs
were high, adoption was low.
Range anxiety, the lack of
charging infrastructure,
plus vacations often involve long-distance
driving, which is a weakness of EV cars.
And this, with the high repair costs,
contributed to an even bigger problem.
Hertz bought tens of thousands of EVs, expecting
them to hold their value well in the used car
market after their rental life was over.
But the opposite happened.
Due to a multitude of factors, like
soft demand, a trade war with China,
as well as an influx of cheaper EVs from
China, prices for EVs began to come down.
Ford had to cut prices of the F-150
Lightning by as much as $7,000.
So what happens when the price of a brand-new car
drops by $7,000? It hammers the resale value of
every used model already on the market.
With all this chaos happening, just
imagine what was happening for Hertz.
Suddenly, the "asset value" part of
Hertz's EV bet looked far worse than for gas cars.
Okay, so their EVs are worth less. So what?
Well, rental car companies
work a little differently.
Rental companies like Hertz
use asset-backed securities.
If Hertz wants a $30,000 car, they borrow $30,000
against it. The bank's security is the car itself.
While holding that car, they’ll rent it out,
let’s say they make $18,000, while paying
off that 30k, with its interest.
Then sell it for maybe $22,000.
They repay the bank, but they made
good rental income, so they profit.
There’s operating costs, and interest of
course, but the main thing is rental cars
are less assets, and more, backed securities.
Hertz isn't really a company that owns half a
million cars. It's a company that operates
half a million cars owned by bondholders.
So… if used-car prices drop, that’s a bigger
difference Hertz has to pay its lenders.
But Hertz's fleet was massive.
So just a 1% drop in used-car
values cost Hertz about $75 million.
This is why they initially went bankrupt.
And when the pandemic killed travel
and briefly tanked used-car prices,
Hertz couldn't keep up with those payments.
But now, it was happening all over
again. Just with EVs.
Hertz also saw $245 million
in charges related to depreciation expenses from
the EV sales. In just the fourth quarter of 2023.
Hertz began selling them off.
20,000 of them, many of which were Teslas,
just 2 years after ordering them.
Many were barely used Tesla Model 3s,
listed as low as $20,000, roughly half of
what it had paid for them a year prior.
The depreciation hit was so severe that
Hertz had to become… creative in unloading
its excess EV inventory.
Hertz began asking
renters if they wanted to buy the EVs.
For example, Hertz offered one customer a
2023 Chevrolet Bolt for about $18,400, and another
a barely year-old Tesla Model 3 for $17,900.
This was bad. But, things
have gotten so much worse.
Way worse.
This move,
while it may have been smart at the time, has
put Hertz in an even worse position, as EVs… have
ironically become the saving grace of rentals?
Now, Hertz are being sued by investors… but
not for selling the EVs.
Something much worse.
But, before we get to that, we need to talk
about another new technology, Hertz embraced.
Since EVs had gone so well. (sarcasm).
We have to talk about Hertz’s strange
experiment… with AI.
AI has undoubtedly
changed at least one industry: coding.
But, this has created a new bottleneck.
There's more AI code than ever,
which means devs now spend more
time reviewing code than writing it.
And reviewing 30,000 lines of code
by hand isn't realistic either.
But a generic agent doesn't fix
it. It can quickly lose context on past pull
requests, comments, changes, or discussion
that happened in Slack, outside the code.
That's why developers use CodeRabbit.
This is CodeRabbit, an AI code review agent
that reads every pull request before it merges,
finds the issues, and fixes them in one click.
It analyzes pull requests, reasons over your
codebase, and gives you easily digestible
feedback before changes are merged.
Reviewing a PR normally means
reconstructing it file by file,
but those files are listed alphabetically, which
tells you nothing about how the change works.
So, use the Change Stack, which
regroups them into cohorts and layers,
so foundations come first and the code depending
on them comes after. But that’s just the start.
Inside the Change Stack, click on the
Overview page.This gives you the full context,
with a summary, actionable blockers, along
with all PR reviews and comments in place.
Then use Timeline View to see the full
chronological story, every change, approval,
comment, so you don’t have to piece together
scattered threads. So you know what happened and,
just as importantly, why it happened.
CodeRabbit is installed on 3 million
repositories, and reviews around 2
million pull requests every week!
Ship better code faster with
CodeRabbit. Try CodeRabbit
by clicking the link in the description.
Thank you to CodeRabbit for sponsoring our videos.
In 2025, Hertz entered a maintenance partnership
with UVeye, worth tens of millions per year.
They said this would be “transforming
its vehicle maintenance process”.
And soon, customers began to experience
the uh… “fruit” of this partnership.
Jessica Fields returned her
Hertz car to the Atlanta airport.
She’s a Hertz Gold member, so, a loyal customer.
But, 17 minutes later, she got a notification,
saying damage was detected.
“I was really mostly confused because I
didn’t see any damage when I dropped off the car,”
She returned, and asked to see the car. But,
Hertz staff refused.
She asked for a manager… she was declined.
So she chased up Hertz again and again,
and she was finally given pictures of
the damage… as well as the charge.
Do you see the terrible state she left
the car in?… Yeah me neither.
Apparently there were two
minuscule dents, in those orange squares.
Fields didn’t see any damage when she dropped
it off, and it sure looks like there’s no damage.
But then, she got the bill.
$160 for the dents… and $190
in administrative fees. $190!
$350 total.
When she tried to dispute the charges,
the email link mysteriously didn’t work.
Thing is, Hertz aren’t the only ones
using AI to detect damages.
But… Hertz are a bit special.
“Some other car rental companies reportedly
use AI as a tool but require human staff to
review before billing customers; however, Hertz
is apparently the only car rental company in the
U.S. that issues damage assessments
to customers without human review.”
Yeah.
So, that $190 for administration,
is basically free revenue for Hertz. Because
it’s not like a human went and looked at it.
It’s not just Fields either
Hertz said that fewer than 3% of vehicles
scanned by the system are billed for damages.
Though, whether that 3% actually have damaged
vehicles is another story.
You could see Hertz’s focus.
Future technology maybe, but primarily: Ways
to cut down costs, by removing areas of labor.
And maybe implicitly, get
more money out of customers.
But, here’s where the story
gets a bit… complicated.
Revenue for Hertz is down
6%. 2024 was also down 3.44%.
But, they’re now making way more money.
(highlight net income and gross income growth).
And, in Q2 2026, they had a
GAAP net income of $64 million.
At least, that’s the way it seems.
In reality, things couldn’t be worse for Hertz.
They are currently drowning in debt, and despite
promising they had strong cash to survive… just a
few weeks later had to go and raise more debt.
Now, they’re being sued.
Plus, there’s the most ironic part of all
of this: The EVs they sold, which turned
out to be a saving grace.
Just not for Hertz.
If you’ve watched this far, consider
subscribing! It helps the channel
and means you won’t miss future videos.
In Q4 2023, Hertz had $245 million of depreciation
charges that quarter alone. So they sold.
After selling them off en masse,
at a huge discount, EVs are now the
best performing segment in the market.
In 2026, the EV index was up 12% year
over year, and non-EVs were up just 1.7%.
So… Hertz bought the peak with EVs,
sold at the bottom, before EVs spiked.
Nice.
For those still holding EVs,
their financials are much better, and their
asset value is up, so depreciation cost is down.
But, Hertz didn't get those
benefits, and potentially even worse,
their stated reason for selling, was wrong.
They sold because they thought EVs wouldn’t
hold value, and now it’s the opposite.
Of course, the market could change again,
but the timing for Hertz couldn’t be worse.
And it gets worse.
In mid-2026 Hertz stated “current unexpected
softness in the used car market” caused losses,
and caused them to adjust their EBITDA forecast.
But… that doesn’t seem to be the case.
“Cox Automotive's Manheim index tells a
different story: the MUVVI reached 212.9
in June, up 2.1% year over year”.
And remember, EVs were up 12%.
Fairly suspicious, which brings us to an
even bigger problem they have right now.
After emerging from their 2020
bankruptcy, Hertz had lost a lot of money.
A net loss of $747 million in 2025,
and a $2.8 billion loss in 2024.
Hertz had no money, and they owed a lot.
Hertz has two giant debt piles. The vehicle debt,
which we talked about in chapter 1, is about
$12.7 billion — car loans backed by cars.
But also, another, non-vehicle
debt. Corporate debt.
Total debt is 18 billion, which makes
their interest expenses pretty big.
259 million just for Q2 2026. And
for the first 6 months, 515 million.
As for Q2 2026, that GAAP net income of
$64 million, wasn’t really from the business.
[Scott Haralson, CFO]: “GAAP net income benefited
from gains on the sale of real estate locations
on which we completed sale-leaseback transactions,
as well as revaluations of other exchangeable
notes and warrants issued in prior years”
Adjusted net loss was actually $47 million.
So, they don’t have money, and have a ton of debt,
which meant a ton of interest, which it’s
already paying with debt, or other means.
So, the question became: how long
can this company keep operating
before it needs to ask someone for money?
Which brings us to their Q1 earnings call,
and Hertz’s liquidity.
The reason they’re being sued,
for misleading shareholders.
In the call, CFO Scott Haralson
said liquidity was $837 million, expected to
reach just under $1 billion by the end of Q2,
and "north of $1.5 billion" by year end.
This is basically the cash they have,
and what they can draw immediately.
Haralson was basically saying that
Hertz has a long runway, and can safely pay their
operating costs and obligations for a good while,
without taking on more debt…
But just six weeks later,
after promising liquidity was good,
Hertz, you guessed it, needed money.
But there was a problem.
No one wants to lend to a
company like Hertz, they’re not doing
well. So, they did something else.
They announced a three hundred and fifty
million dollar bond, at 6.75% interest.
They then cut their profit forecast to
somewhere between fifty and eighty million.
To get that 350 million, they issued new
shares, 37 million of them, and lent them
to JPMorgan Chase, and this is crazy.
“one of its affiliates intends to sell
the Borrowed Shares and use the resulting
short position to facilitate transactions
by which investors in the Notes.
The activity described above could
affect the market price of the Common Stock”.
Basically, Hertz lent them shares to short,
aka betting against Hertz’s stock, which
Hertz doesn’t receive proceeds from.
Not only was their liquidity promise, just
not true, but to get more capital, they
had to let someone bet against their own stock.
Even worse… there wasn’t enough stock around to
borrow to do so. Roughly 30% of the tradable
stock is sold short, about 10 times what a
normal company carries.
They just made more,
diluting existing shareholders.
So, you can probably guess what happened next.
The allegation is that Hertz told investors the
money was fine when it knew this was coming.
Strangely enough, the lawsuit named the
defendants as the company, of course,
but also CEO Gil West, and CFO Scott Haralson.
The most ironic thing, I think,
is that Hertz technically hit their goal.
It landed at $984 million in liquidity.
Just, to GET that liquidity, it needed
more debt, and to dilute shares.
It’s not a bad time to be a rental car
company, but boy is it a bad time to be Hertz.
They’re barely a company at this point, and
more a debt and interest paying machine.
Little profit, high liabilities.
Will they collapse? Who knows.
But their current state might be even worse.
Hertz isn't the only car company in
a strange position.
You might recognize
this. The Carvana vending machine.
A used car dealership which somehow
ended up on the S&P 500.
And, the whole thing
might be a gigantic pump & dump.
Click here to learn the rest of the story.